Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is קי''א, kuf yud
alef, סנהדרין Sanhedrin 111. We pick up on קי''א עמוד ב' kuf
yud alef amud bet at the
משנה mishna middle of the page, and we have been discussing who
is and isn't or who isn't going to get a portion in
the world to come, and now we turn to the ten tribes
who were sent into exile.
So let's take a look at the משנה. mishna. עשרת השבטים אינם
עתידים לחזור: aseret hashvatim einam atidim lachzor: the ten tribes will not
in the future return.
שנאמר, shenemar, as the פסוק pasuk says, וישלכם אל ארץ אחרת כיום
הזה: vayashlichem el eretz acheret kayom hazeh: and he cast them into
a different land as this very day. And as רש''י Rashi points
out, we're assuming this is talking about the ten tribes because they
were all cast out at once to one place. Anyway, and the
דרשה drasha is on the word כיום הזה. kayom hazeh. מה היום
הולך ואינו חוזר: mah hayom holech ve'eino chozer: the same way a
day goes, evaporates, and no longer will come back, אף הם הולכים
ואינם חוזרים: af heim holchim ve'einam chozrim: they will go and not
come back. דברי רבי עקיבא: divrei Rabbi Akiva: what Rabbi Akiva says.
Now the language here חוזרים chozrim sounds like we're not talking about
whether they have a portion in the world to come, but whether
they will return, meaning are there ever going to be twelve tribes
of Israel again? Will those ten tribes in the future times, in
ימות המשיח yemos hamashiach or עולם הבא, olam haba, however it's understood,
will they, will we find out who they are, where they're scattered,
and their identities will be known and will they return and will
we once again have twelve tribes or not? And it sounds like
Rabbi Akiva is saying no, that will not happen, which is pretty
shocking as a statement of a vision of a national future, and
also a number of הלכות halachot won't apply if we don't have
all twelve tribes back, like יובל yovel and שמיטה shmita and so
on. So
but that seems to be what Rabbi Akiva is saying, that we're
not talking anymore about whether they'll be resurrected, but what will be
of their descendants? Will their descendants ever return? Although רש''י Rashi sort
of goes back and forth between saying whether this is talking about
their descendants coming
back to the land of Israel or whether it's talking about the
original generation. Okay. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: כיום הזה, מה
היום מאפיל ומאיר. kayom hazeh, mah hayom ma'afil ume'ir. Rabbi Eliezer says
no, you're wrong, and it's like this day: the same way a
day darkens and then gives light, אף עשרת השבטים שאפלה להם, כך
עתידה להאיר להם: af aseret hashvatim she'afela lahem, kach atida leha'ir lahem:
even the ten tribes that it was dark for them, it will
be light for them once more in the future. Okay. תנו רבנן:
tanu rabanan: עשרת השבטים אינם חלק לעולם הבא. aseret hashvatim einam chelek
le'olam haba. So this ברייתא brayta does not use the word לחזור,
lachzor, or not לחזור lachzor at least not in the beginning, and
it says they don't have a portion in the world to come.
שנאמר: shenemar: ויתשם ה' מעל אדמתם באף ובחמה ובקצף גדול וישלכם אל
ארץ אחרת כיום הזה. vayitashem hashem me'al admatam be'af uvchema uvketzef gadol
vayashlichem el eretz acheret kayom hazeh. ויתשם ה' מעל אדמתם: vayitashem hashem
me'al admatam: he cast them from the land בעולם הזה, ba'olam hazeh,
in this world, וישלכם אל ארץ אחרת vayashlichem el eretz acheret לעולם
הבא: le'olam haba: cast them to a different place in the future
world.
דברי רבי עקיבא: divrei Rabbi Akiva: so like our משנה, mishna, except
here it's about עולם הבא, olam haba, not about whether they will
return. So here it seems to be about the people themselves,
the ones who were exiled, that they will not be resurrected. Okay.
רבי שמעון בן יהודה איש כפר עכו אומר משום רבי שמעון: Rabbi
Shimon ben Yehuda ish kefir akko omer mishum Rabbi Shimon: Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehuda said in the name of Rabbi Shimon the original, אם
מעשיהם כיום הזה אינם חוזרים ואם לאו חוזרים. im ma'aseihem kayom hazeh
einam chozrim ve'im lav chozrim.
So he introduces the term חוזר, chozer, and he says if they
continue to act as they have on this day when they were
exiled, then they will not return. But if they do not continue
to act as they have on that day, if they do תשובה,
teshuvah, then they will return. So again, this חוזר chozer makes it
sound like we're talking about their descendants, because the descendants are the
ones that can change their actions. The people who died are dead,
their actions can't change. Okay, so he goes to the חוזר chozer
language and it sounds like we're talking about their descendants. And now
though, however, the ברייתא brayta returns to the עולם הבא olam haba
language. רבי
אומר: Rebbi omer: באים הם לעולם הבא: ba'im heim le'olam haba: no,
they will come לעולם הבא. le'olam haba. שנאמר: shenemar: והיה ביום ההוא
יתקע בשופר גדול ובאו האובדים בארץ אשור: vehaya bayom hahu yitaka bashofar
gadol uva'u ha'ovdim be'eretz ashur:
those who have been exiled to the land of אשור, Ashur, Assyria,
and that was סנחריב Sennacherib who exiled the ten tribes. So it's
right there in the פסוק pasuk that they will come back. And
by the way, that פסוק pasuk though you'll notice is right seems
to be talking about not resurrection, but about the descendants, that the
descendants will come back. So very unclear here whether all this discussion
is about whether that generation itself that died will be resurrected or
not, or whether it means whether their descendants will return or not.
Okay. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן: amar Rabba bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan: שבקיה רבי עקיבא לחסידותיה. shavkiah Rabbi Akiva
lechasidutei. Rabbi Akiva abandoned
his
compassion, his
חסד, chesed, because the same way we said before, he abandoned his
compassion by saying that the דור המדבר dor hamidbar won't have a
portion in the world to come, here too, he's so ready to
say that the ten tribes won't return or won't have a portion
in the world to come, and he forgot his compassionate side. And
there's obviously פסוקים psukim you could have quoted that would have supported
that they do. Let's take a look. שנאמר: shenemar: הלוך וקראת את
הדברים האלה צפונה ואמרת שובה משובה ישראל: haloch vekarata et hadevarim ha'eleh
tzafona ve'amarta shuva meshiva yisrael: go call these things to
the
north. לא אטור לעולם, lo ator le'olam, I will not hold the
enmity forever. So I will not begrudge it forever. So here God
says I will have חסד chesed on you and I will bring
you back. And Rabbi Akiva forgot that חסד chesed and to be
able to interpret that the ten tribes will return.
Okay, מאי חסידותיה? mai chasidutei? Now where do you see that he
had that חסד, chesed, that he did show that compassion in his
understanding of things relating to the world to come? דתניא, Detanya, we
learned in a ברייתא: braita: קטני בני רשעי ישראל אין להם חלק
לעולם הבא. Katnei bnei rishay yisrael ein lahem chelek le'olam haba. The
small ones of the רשעים resha'im of Israel do not have a
portion in the world to come. שנאמר, Shene'emar, כי הנה היום בא
בער כתנור, ki hineh hayom ba boer katanur, a day burning as
fire, והיו כל זדים וכל עשי רשעה קש, vehayu kol zeidim vechol
osei rish'ah kash, all of the wicked will be like stubble, ולהט
אותם היום הבא, velahet otam hayom haba, and it will inflame them
the future day, אמר השם צבאות אשר לא יעזוב להם שורש וענף,
amar hashem tzevaot asher lo ya'azov lahem shoresh ve'anaf,
no root and no branch will be left to them.
שורש בעולם הזה, Shoresh ba'olam hazeh, they won't have a root in
this world, וענף לעולם הבא, ve'anaf le'olam haba, and a branch in
the world to come, so they won't have the progeny. Now what
does this mean? Because somebody is a רשע, rasha, their kid won't
have עולם הבא? olam haba? I mean the גמרא's gemara's constant, I
mean the תורה's Torah's against it: לא יומתו אבות על בנים ובנים
לא יומתו על אבות. lo yumtu avot al banim uvanim lo yumtu
al avot. I mean, somebody would be punished because their parent is
a רשע? rasha? It doesn't make any sense. So the general explanation
of this is that it's referring to
the children that died while they were still young before they became
adults and they were being maybe even understood that they were being
punished for the sins of their parents, which also is like a
type of an idea that is also present in various places in
תנ"ך Tanakh and in the גמרא gemara about children dying for the
sins of the parents even though it goes against לא יומתו אבות
על בנים. lo yumtu avot al banim. But anyway, so those children
that died as an extension of their parents, will they have a
portion in the world to come? Still seems terribly unfair, but at
least that's at least some way to read it.
Okay, רש"י Rashi says,
the last line of רש"י: Rashi: קטני רשעי ישראל אלו בניהם שלקטנים
ולא חטאו פליגי בהו. Katnei rishay yisrael elu bneihem shektanim velo chatu
palgi behu.
If their children are minor and presumably they died, what is their
story? The רשעים resha'im themselves won't have a portion, what about their
kids? Now I should also pause to say until this time we've
been talking about very particular generations that don't have a portion, people
that do particularly wicked things, האומר אין תורה מן השמים, ha'omer ein
torah min hashamayim, and now we are reverting to a default assumption
that all the רשעים resha'im don't have a portion in the world
to come, which tends to be not just special רשעים, resha'im, which
tends to actually be the more common sort of theology in the
גמרא. gemara. Okay, so not only do the רשעים resha'im not have
a portion in the world to come, even their children do not
based on this פסוק. pasuk. That's what רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says.
רבי עקיבא אומר באים הם לעולם הבא, Rabbi Akiva omer ba'im hem
le'olam haba, no
they will get עולם הבא, olam haba, שנאמר שומר פתאים השם, shene'emar
shomer peta'im hashem,
God watches the foolish, but here meaning rather the children, שכן קורים
בכרכי הים לינוקא פסיא sheken korim bekarchei hayam liyanuka pasya
because they call in the islands, they call a child a פסיא.
pasya. Okay, so God will protect the children. ואומר Ve'omer and the
פסוק pasuk says: גדו אילנא וחבלוהי, godu ilana vechabluhi, chop down the
tree and destroy it, ברם עיקר שרשוהי בארעא שבוקו, beram ikar shoreshohi
be'ar'a shevoku, but leave
the root in the ground. So even if the wicked person is
cut down, the children will be left
to grow after him. Again, or at least be resurrected in עולם
הבא. olam haba. ואלא מה אני מקיים לא יעזוב להם שורש וענף?
Ve'ela mah ani mekayem lo ya'azov lahem shoresh ve'anaf?
Then no root or branch will be left? שלא יניח להם לא
מצוה ולא שיורי מצוה, shelo yanich lahem lo mitzvah velo shiyurei mitzvah,
that when the רשעים resha'im are punished, God will not leave even
the remnant of a מצוה mitzvah that God has not rewarded them
for, and God will reward them for all of their good deeds
so that ultimately they can be punished לעולם הבא. le'olam haba. דבר
אחר, Davar acher, another explanation: שורש זו נשמה וענף זו הגוף, Shoresh
zu neshamah ve'anaf zu haguf, that neither their soul nor their body
will be left, so that means that they won't be resurrected in
the עולם הבא. olam haba.
אבל קטני בני רשעי עובדי כוכבים, Aval katnei bnei rishay ovdei kochavim,
so that's the debate about the minors, the small children of רשעי
ישראל. rishay yisrael. But the minors of רשעי עובדי כוכבים, rishay ovdei
kochavim, of the non-Jews, דברי הכל divrei hakol
everybody agrees: אין באים לעולם הבא, ein ba'im le'olam haba, they do
not get a portion to the world to come. Not only do
their parents who are רשעים resha'im not get a portion, but the
children as well.
And by the way though, what's implicit about this is that חסידי
אומות העולם chasidei umot ha'olam do have a portion in the world
to come, which is
debated in the ברייתא, braita, in the תוספתא, Tosefta, and so on,
but that is implicit here. So a lot of things, after we've
been learning about all these special cases that only these people don't
have a portion in the world to come, here we find out
that רשעים, resha'im, all רשעים resha'im do not, and there's even a
question about
the children of the רשעים resha'im and there we distinguish between Jews
and non-Jews, but also we also see a very important
assumption. Actually, these words רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel should probably be taken
out and it should just be נפקא ליה nafka lei מן mi
ותאבד כל זכר למו, v'tavad kol zakhar lamo, all remnant of them
will be destroyed talking about the רשעים reshaim of the non-Jews. Okay,
so the רשעים reshaim of the non-Jews and their kids don't have
a portion to the world to come, but they themselves do, the
צדקי אומות העולם tzidkei umot haolam do have a portion in the
world to come. איתמר, Itmar, so anyway that's where רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva showed greater חסד chesed because there רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was
saying that the קטנים ktanim do have a portion and it was
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who was saying that they do not. איתמר
Itmar was taught, קטן מאימתי בא לעולם הבא? Katan meaimatai ba l'olam
haba? At what stage, forget that the father's a רשע, rasha, you
know normal case, or we פוסקן pasken that the בני רשעים bnei
reshaim do have a חלק לעולם הבא chelek l'olam haba like רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, fine. What stage does the child have ascension, this
is saying a נשמה neshama that will live on into the world
to come? You know, the גמרא Gemara asks elsewhere like what time
does the נשמה neshama get into the גוף? guf? It's a similar
type of a question. When is that soul developed to the point
that if the child dies, that there will be a resurrection, that
soul gets עולם הבא? olam haba? Okay, קטן מאימתי בא לעולם הבא?
Katan meaimatai ba l'olam haba? רבי חייא ורבי שמעון ברבי. Rabbi Chiyya
v'Rabbi Shimon bar Rabbi.
חד אמר, Chad amar, one says
משעה שנולד, mishaa shenolad, from the very day he was born, then
if he dies then he'll have a portion in the world to
come. וחד אמר, V'chad amar, משעה שסיפר, mishaa shesiper, from the time
he begins to be
able to talk.
מאן דאמר Man d'amar משעה שנולד mishaa shenolad כדנאמר kdeneemar יבואו ויגידו
צדקתו לעם נולד, yavou v'yagidu tzidkato l'am nolad, they will tell God's
righteousness to the nation that has been born, so as soon as
they're born, כי עשה ki asa what was done. ומאן דאמר Uman
d'amar משעה שסיפר mishaa shesiper דכתיב זרע יעבדנו dichtiv zera yaavdenu יסופר
yesupar, לה' לדור, the seed that will worship him, that will speak
to God for the generations. So זרע, zera, so it says יסופר,
yesupar when it is יסופר able to talk, then it will be
for future generations, will be resurrected.
איתמר Itmar was taught, רבינא אמר Ravina amar משעה שנזרע mishaa shenizra
from the very moment he was conceived, which is again interesting, does
that have הלכה halakha implications for you know for when something is
a life according to Jewish law? No, it does not. Very different
questions: when does a soul enter, when will it get עולם הבא,
olam haba, when הלכה halakha is it a life? Anyway from the
moment it was conceived, דכתיב dichtiv זרע יעבדנו the seed will worship
you. נחמן בר יצחק אמר Nachman bar Yitzchak amar משעה שנימול mishaa
shenimol from the day he's given a
ברית מילה, brit milah, דכתיב אני עני וגוע מנוער dichtiv ani ani
v'goveia mi-noar נשאתי אימתך אפונה, nasati ematcha afunah, I,
I and you know expiration the way רש''י Rashi explains it from
גזיזה gizia even from youth would be a real death and I
have I have carried the fear of You and
it's come upon me. So it's very hard to know what that
has to do with ברית מילה brit milah but רש''י Rashi says
I got a ברית מילה brit milah because of my fear of
You and from that moment my death would be a real death
in the sense that my soul would get עולם הבא, olam haba,
very hard to see how they exactly learn that from that פסוק.
pasuk. Anyway this might have something to do with you know a
whole practice about why if a child dies even before his eighth
birthday he has a ברית מילה, brit milah, they do a ברית
מילה brit milah before a boy before burying him, it's also based
on like another מדרש midrash that אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu stands by
the gates of גן עדן Gan Eden and will only let male
children who've had a ברית מילה brit milah enter. תנא משום Tana
mishum רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir משעה שיאמר אמן mishaa yomar Amen from the time
he's able to say אמן, Amen, שנאמר פתחו שערים ויבוא גוי צדיק
שומר אמונים, sheneemar pitchu shearim v'yavo goy tzaddik shomer emunim, let the
holy nation the righteous nation that keeps the faith. אל תקרי שומר
אמונים אלא שומר אמונים. Al tikrei shomer emunim ela shomer amenim. Okay,
those who are able to say אמן, Amen, that person is considered
to maybe now have you know be able to participate somehow religiously
some type of affirmation and therefore does that that soul will get
עולם הבא. olam haba. מאי אמן? Mai Amen? Top of ק''יא ע''א,
kuf yud aleph amud aleph, what is the significance of אמן Amen
being a way of showing affirmation? אמר רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Chanina
אל מלך נאמן Kel Melech Ne'eman as you know God is the
trustworthy King, so as God is my witness type of a thing,
you know affirming something by
God God
Himself. לכן הרחיבה שאול נפשה ופערה פיה לבלי חוק, Lachen hirchiva sheol
nafsha u'fara piha livli chok, therefore שאול sheol has opened up its
soul
and yawned open its mouth without without any you know limit.
אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish למי שמשייר אפילו חוק אחד, l'mi
shemeshayer afilu chok echad, so לבלי חוק, livli chok, who is going
to go into גיהנום Gehennam to whom has the depths opened up
its mouth? To the person who abandoned even one חוק, chok, does
not do even one מצוה. mitzvah.
אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan said רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. לא
ניחא למריהו דאמרת להו הכי. lo nicha lemareihu deamartu lehu hachi. It's
not good for their master, to God, that you have said this
about God's creatures, that even somebody who just doesn't do one מצוה
mitzvah is going to get גיהנום. Gehennom. אלא אפילו לא למד אלא
חוק אחד. ella afilu lo lamad ella chok echad. Even if somebody
only learns one one law, they'll be saved from גיהנום. Gehennom. Only
somebody who has never done any מצוה mitzvah will get
גיהנום. Gehennom. Okay, not hasn't done one, who hasn't done any. והיה
בכל הארץ נאם ה' פי שנים בה יכרתו ויגועו והשלישית ייוותר בה.
vehaya bechol haaretz neum Hashem pi shenayim bah yikareitu veyigva'u vehashlishit yivater
bah. Okay, and it will be, this is just דרשנ'ינג darshaning פסוקים
pesukim about גיהנום Gehennom or about the future days. It will be
in the whole, in the entire land, says God, double what, that
will be cut off and will expire, and a third will be,
will remain, in this like גוג ומגוג Gog uMagog or in the
future times. So אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, שלישי של שם.
shlishi shel Shem. This doesn't mean a third of all humanity, it
means a third of שם, Shem, the son of נח. Noach. Okay.
השלישית ייוותר בה, hashlishit yivater bah, the, the somehow they're making a
דרשה drasha that it's not just one third, but a third of
a third. נח Noach had three sons, so a third of שם
Shem will remain.
I mean רש"י Rashi even goes even further on a third of
a third of a third of that. But anyway, this גמרא Gemara
just seems to say a third of שם. Shem. אמר רבי יוחנן
לא ניחא למריהו דאמרת להו הכי. Amar Rabi Yochanan lo nicha lemareihu
deamartu lehu hachi. It's not good for their master that you have
said this, meaning that you are going to basically say eight ninths
of the world will be destroyed. אלא אפילו שלישי של נח. ella
afilu shlishi shel Noach. No, just one third of נח, Noach, meaning
only two thirds of the world will be destroyed, not eight ninths
of it. All right, רש"י Rashi has a slightly different read but
I think this is the פשט. pshat. כי אנכי בעלתי בכם ולקחתי
אתכם אחד מעיר ושנים ממשפחה, ki anochi baalti bachem velakachti etchem echad
me'ir ushnayim mimishpacha, because I have taken ownership over you, one way
to read that, and I've taken you one out of each town
and two from a family. It really should be two out of
a town and one from a family, but sometimes Hebrew poetic sort
of reverses it like that. Anyway, only a tiny remnant will be
saved in the future times. אמר ריש לקיש דברים ככתבן, Amar Reish
Lakish devarim kichtavan, just like it sounds like, only this tiny remnant.
אמר ליה רבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rabi Yochanan, said רבי יוחנן Rabi
Yochanan back to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, so you, this is the
whole theme, right? Where ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is a very strict
read, sort of like when רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva forgot his compassion,
and רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan responds, it's not God doesn't appreciate, their
creator, God doesn't appreciate, their master, that you've dictated such a heavy
judgment for God's creature. Okay, so he says, yeah, only a tiny
bit will be
saved. אמר ליה רבי יוחנן לא ניחא למריהו דאמרת להו הכי. Amar
lei Rabi Yochanan lo nicha lemareihu deamartu lehu hachi. It is not
good for their master to God that you said this about God's
creature. אלא אחד מעיר מזכה כל העיר. ella echad me'ir mezakeh kol
ha'ir. The opposite, if there is just one in the entire town,
on his merit the entire town will be saved.
מזכה כל העיר. mezakeh kol ha'ir. שנים ממשפחה מזכה כל המשפחה, shnayim
mimishpacha mezakeh kol hamishpacha, and two out of a family will protect
the whole family. חזייה דהוה קא חייף רישיה וסליק ויתיב קמיה דרב.
chazyei dahavei ka chayif reishei vesalik veyasiv kamei deRav. So רבי יוחנן
Rabi Yochanan saw that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish was, you know, was
like
scratching his hair or like de-lousing his hair or rubbing, combing it.
Anyway, he was sitting in front of his רבי, Rebbi, you know,
for, for
learning תורה. Torah. Okay, so and then he, so he was spending
way too much time on his personal appearance before he went to
sit and to learn. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said to
him,
I'm sorry, I skipped a whole line here, didn't I?
Yes, I'm sorry, I thought that did not make sense. Jumping back,
okay. ושנים ממשפחה מזכה כל משפחה כולה. ushnayim mimishpacha mezakeh kol mishpacha
kullah. יתיב רב כהנא קמיה דרב. yasiv Rav Kahana kamei deRav. That's
why we're talking about רב Rav here, so not רבי יוחנן. Rabi
Yochanan. Okay, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana was sitting in front of
רב. Rav. יתיב וקאמר דברים ככתבן, yasiv veka'amar devarim kichtavan, same debate
of רבי יוחנן ריש לקיש. Rabi Yochanan Reish Lakish. אמר ליה רב
לא ניחא למריהו דאמרת להו הכי. Amar lei Rav lo nicha lemareihu
deamartu lehu hachi. No, it's not good for their master for for
God that you've said this about God's creature that, you know, it's
all that only one out of each town will be saved. אלא
אחד מעיר מזכה העיר ושנים ממשפחה מזכה כל משפחה. ella echad me'ir
mezakeh ha'ir veshnayim mimishpacha mezakeh kol mishpacha. Okay, that's why I skipped
because it was exact same same line. Now, חזייה רב, chazyei Rav,
רב Rav saw רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, okay, דהוה קא חייף רישיה
וסליק ויתיב קמיה דרב. dahavei ka chayif reishei vesalik veyasiv kamei deRav.
That first he was, you know, combing his hair, making himself look
really nice and good, and then he would go and sit in
front of the ישיבה. yeshiva. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רב Rav
said to רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, ולא תמצא בארץ החיים. velo timatzei
be'eretz hachayim. So will not be found in the land of the
living. So it sounded like he was saying, you know, oh you're
spending so much בטלה battala time, worried so much about your appearance,
you won't get עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, at least that's what it
sounds like on the surface. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רב כהנא
Rav Kahana said back to רב, Rav, מילט קא לייט ליה, milet
ka layet lei, are you cursing me? אמר ליה קרא קאמינא. Amar
lei kra kamina. No, no, no, I'm just telling you the פסוק,
pasuk, it's what the פסוק pasuk says, I'm not cursing I'm reading
a פסוק. pasuk. But the real point is I'm not saying you're
not getting עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, this is what I'm saying. לא
תמצא תורה במי שמחיה עצמו עליה. lo timatzei Torah bemi shemechayeh atzmo
aleiha. לא תמצא בארץ החיים, lo timatzei be'eretz hachayim, you won't find
תורה Torah if you're having such a good life. Okay, you have
to be ממית עצמו עליה, mamit atzmo aleiha, you have to be
sacrifice, privation, you have to be offended, so comfortable, the way you're
learning תורה, Torah, it's not how you're going to get קניין kinyan
on תורה. Torah. All right, so that was a little digression from
לא ניחא ליה למריהו lo nicha lei lemareihu
discussion of רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. תנא, tana,
we תנא, tana, it was taught in a ברייתא. beraita. רבי סימאי
אומר. Rabbi Simai omer. נאמר ולקחתי אתכם לי לעם, ne'emar velakachti etchem
li le'am, I will take you for Me as a people. ונאמר
והבאתי אתכם, vene'emar veheveisi etchem, and I will bring you into the
land. This is a sort of like leading up to
פסח, Pesach, ולקחתי והבאתי. velakachti veheveisi. מקיש יציאת מצרים לביאתם לארץ. makiash
yetzias Mitzrayim levi'asom la'aretz. It compares their going into...
their leaving from Egypt to their going into the land. מה ביאתם
לארץ שנים מששים רבוא. ma bi'asom la'aretz shenayim mishishim ribbo. So once
again we're dealing with how many of... much of humanity is going
to remain or how much of the Jewish people is going to
remain in the future times at the מלחמת גוג ומגוג. Milchemes Gog
uMagog. So when they left Egypt, there were 600,000 that came out,
men between the ages of 20 and 60. And of those 600,000
that came out of Egypt, how many went into the land? Two,
right? יהושע וכלב. Yehoshua veKalev. So, so מה ביאתם לארץ שנים מששים
רבוא. ma bi'asom la'aretz shenayim mishishim ribbo. So if that was true
when they get... when they went into the land, there was two
out of
600,000. אף יציאתם ממצרים שנים מששים רבוא. af yetziasam miMitzrayim shenayim mishishim
ribbo. So when they came out of Egypt, when 600,000 came out,
that 600,000 represented two out of every 600,000 that were left behind.
Or in other words, 600,000
times 300,000, right? What is that? Oh my god, I can't even
do that math. Okay, some type of billion, trillion, whatever. Anyway, that's
how many were in Egypt. The 600,000 that came out were really
a proportion of two to every 600,000, just like when they went
into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, what went in was two out of
every 600,000. So in those, in that original redemption, that was the
proportions. And that's sort of echoing what we're talking about here about
what will be the proportions that will remain and that will be
destroyed at the time of the future redemption. אמר רבא, amar Rava,
וכן לימות המשיח. vechen limos haMashiach. And as I was saying, and
the same will be true in Messianic times, only two out of
every 600,000 will be left. אוי. oy. שנאמר shene'emar as it says:
וענתה שמה כימי נעוריה וכיום עלותה מארץ מצרים, ve'ansah shamah kimei ne'ureha
vekiyom alosah me'eretz Mitzrayim, she be answered there like the days of
her youth and like the days when she went out of Egypt.
So the same when she went out of Egypt, only two out
of every 600,000 Jews were saved, the same it is saying will
be לעתיד לבוא. le'asid lavo. תניא, Tanya, אמר רבי אלעזר בר רבי
יוסי, amar Rabbi Elazar bar Rabbi Yose, פעם אחת נכנסתי לאלכסנדריה של
מצרים. pa'am achas nichnasti le-Alexandria shel Mitzrayim. Once I went into Alexandria
in Egypt. מצאתי זקן אחד ואמר לי, matzasi zaken echad ve'amar li,
and I found a certain old man and he said to me:
בוא ואראך מה עשו אבותי לאבותיך, bo ve'arekha mah asu avosai la'avosayicha,
come, let me show you what my forefathers did to your forefathers.
מהם טבעו בים, mehem tav'u bayam, מהם הרגו בחרב, mehem hargu becharev,
מהם מעכו בבנין. mehem machu bevinyan. Some of them they, you know,
drowned in the sea, you know, with the... the מילדות העבריות, meyaldos
ha'ivriyos, you know, when he says לכל עמו לאמר: lechol ammo leimor:
כל הבן הילוד היאורה תשליכהו. kol haben hayillod hayora tashlichuhu. Some of
them were killed by the sword and some of them they, presumably
like when they were enslaved, and some of them they crushed into
the... into the structures. ועל דבר זה נענש משה רבינו, ve'al davar
zeh ne'enash Moshe Rabbeinu, and for this משה Moshe was punished, שנאמר
shene'emar as it says: ומאז באתי אל פרעה לדבר בשמך הרע לעם
הזה. ume'az basi el Paroh ledabber bishmekha hera la'am hazeh. So when
from the, you know, משה's Moshe complaining to God, from the day
I came to פרעה Paroh all you've done is done evil. אמר
לו הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar lo HaKadosh Baruch Hu, God said to
משה: Moshe: חבל על דאבדין ולא משתכחין, chaval al de'avdin velo mishtachchin,
woe to those, to the ones that were lost and can no
longer be found. You know, משה, Moshe, you're not like the previous
generation. I mourn the previous generation that had so much אמונה emunah
in Me. הרי כמה פעמים נגליתי אל אברהם יצחק ויעקב באל שדי.
harei kamma pe'amim nigleisi el Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov be'E-l Shaddai. Many times
I revealed myself to אברהם, Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, and יעקב, Yaakov, and
not in the יוד קא ואו קא Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei name. You know, the
whole thing of them, משה Moshe says מה שמו, mah shemo, and
He says אהיה אשר אהיה, Ehyeh asher Ehyeh, כה תאמר, ko tomar,
you know, השם אלקי אבותיכם שלחני אליכם. Hashem Elokei avoseichem shelachani aleichem.
You know, and at the beginning of וארא: Va'era: וארא אל אברהם
אל יצחק ואל יעקב באל שדי ושמי השם לא נודעתי להם. va'era
el Avraham el Yitzchak ve'el Yaakov be'E-l Shaddai ushemi Hashem lo nodati
lahem. So the fact that it doesn't say יוד קא ואו קא
Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei earlier when God talks to אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov
is a separate conversation, but for now in some meaningful way, you
know, רש"י Rashi says it doesn't mean they didn't know the name,
but God didn't demonstrate the fulfillment of the name. But okay, for
some, in some meaningful way, the relationship to אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham
Yitzchak veYaakov was with אל שדי. E-l Shaddai. So God is saying,
you know, for אברהם יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov I only revealed
Myself to them in the אל שדי E-l Shaddai mode, ולא הרהרו
מדותי, velo hirheru middosai, and they never questioned, you know, they had
faith in Me and whether I was going to fulfill My promises.
They, they never challenged Me. ולא אמרו לי מה שמך, velo amru
li mah shemekha, and they never asked Me for My name. אמרתי
לאברהם: amarti le-Avraham: קום התהלך בארץ לארכה ולרחבה כי לך אתננה, kum
hishalech ba'aretz le'orkah ulerochbah ki lecha etnenah, give you the land. ביקש
מקום לקבור שרה, bikaish makom likvor Sarah, and then came the time
that he had to bury שרה, Sarah, ולא מצא עד שקנה בארבע
מאות שקל כסף, velo matza ad shekanah be'arba me'os shekel kesef, and
he had to buy, you know, at the high, high prices of
400 שקל, shekel, and he never said, God, where's the promise? You
promised me that this land will be mine. He just faithfully accepted
My judgment and My actions. ולא הרהר אחר מדותי. velo hirhir achar
middosai. אמרתי ליצחק: amarti le-Yitzchak: גור בארץ הזאת ואהיה עמך ואברכך, gur
ba'aretz hazos ve'ehyeh imcha va'avarekheka, stay in this land and I'll be
with you and bless you. ביקש עבדיו מים לשתות, bikaish avadav mayim
lishtos, and when they wanted to find water, ולא מצאו עד שעשו
מריבה, velo matzu ad she'asu merivah, they had to, you know, he
had to just hold onto some water rights, let's say, a fight.
שנאמר: shene'emar: ויריבו רועי גרר עם רועי יצחק לאמר לנו המים, vayyarivu
ro'ei Gerar im ro'ei Yitzchak leimor: lanu hamayim, and they fought with
the shepherds of גרר. Gerar. ולא הרהר אחר מדותי, velo hirhir achar
middosai, and יצחק Yitzchak didn't say, God... God, what about your promise
that you'll be with me? אמרתי ליעקב, amarti leYaakov, I said to
יעקב, Jacob, הארץ אשר אתה שוכב עליה לך אתננה, ha'aretz asher ata
shochev aleha lecha etnenah, this land that you are lying on I
will give it to you. ביקש מקום לנטוע אהלו, bikash makom linto'a
ohalo, and he looked and when he was looking for a place
to simply pitch his tent, just to stay, ולא מצא שקנה במאה
קשיטה, velo matza shekana beme'ah kesitah, he had to buy, you know,
this place by שכם Shechem for a hundred קשיטה. kesitah. ולא הרהר
אחר מידותי, velo hirher achar midotai, he didn't say, God, where's the
promise you promised to give me the land? They had faith that
the promise would be fulfilled, they didn't ask to reveal myself, what's
his name, they didn't ask to understand me better, they just listened.
Okay, ולא אמרו לי מה שמך, velo amru li mah shemecha, they
didn't say what's your name? ואתה אמרת לי מה שמך בתחילה, ve'ata
amarta li mah shemecha betechila, first you asked for my name and
עכשיו אתה אומר לי והצל לא הצלת את עמך, ve'achshav ata omer
li vehatzel lo hitzalta et amecha, you haven't saved your people. This
is a great פשט pshat on that first פסוק pasuk in פרשת
וארא. Parshat Va'eira. ועתה תראה, ve'ata tireh, now you'll see, אשר אעשה
לפרעה, asher e'eseh lePharaoh, what I will do to פרעה Pharaoh you'll
see. במלחמת פרעה אתה רואה ואי אתה רואה במלחמת שלושים ואחד מלכים,
bemilchemet Pharaoh ata ro'eh ve'i ata ro'eh bemilchemet shloshim ve'echad melachim, and
you will not see though what's going to happen to the thirty-one
kings because of your lack of faith you will not go into
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, now pause. Okay, what does this so
that's
a very powerful דרש drash on that opening פסוק pasuk in פרשת
וארא. Parshat Va'eira. What does this have to do with this Alexandrian
showed me and says this is what my forefathers did to your
forefathers and משה Moshe was punished. What does it mean משה Moshe
was punished? So what it means is that when משה Moshe saw,
you know, what was being done to the Jewish people and he
complained to God, that complaining to God got him punished. All right,
so the Egyptians did horrible things and and God, ultimately, and משה,
Moshe, because he wasn't able to tolerate that and he challenged God,
that in the end led to this punishment. Some of us sort
of feel like, good for you, משה, Moshe, by challenging God, but
that doesn't seem to be the point here. Although interestingly the גמרא
Gemara immediately, you know, speaks about then how God reveals Godself with
God's name to משה, Moshe, skips to those פסוקים psukim by הר
סיני, Har Sinai, another case of God revealing Godself to משה. Moshe.
וימהר משה ויקוד ארצה וישתחו, vayimaher Moshe vayikod artza vayishtachu, משה Moshe
act quickly went and he and he prostrated himself. מה ראה, mah
ra'ah, what did he see that it led him to prostrate himself?
So מה ראה משה, mah ra'ah Moshe, רבי חנינא בן גמליאל Rabbi
Chanina ben Gamliel says ארך אפים ראה. erech apayim ra'ah. He saw
when God revealed, you know, that was when God revealed the י"ג
מידות yud-gimel midot and the מידה mida of ארך אפים, erech apayim,
so that משה Moshe was so taken by that it led him
to to bow down. רבנן אמרי Rabbanan amri אמת ראה, emet ra'ah,
no he saw God's מידה mida of of justice, of דין, din,
of אמת. emet. Okay, so and the way רש"י Rashi explains, so
as opposed to the first case, he was bowing down because he
was grateful for the מידה mida of ארך אפים, erech apayim, here
he was bowing down to pray that God did not use the
מידה mida of justice against בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. תניא כמאן דאמר
ארך אפים ראה, Tanya keman de'amar erech apayim ra'ah, we talk about
like the one who says ארך אפים ראה, erech apayim ra'ah, דתניא
כשעלה משה למרום, detanya keshe'ala Moshe lamarom, when משה Moshe went up
to the to the highs, מצאו להקדוש ברוך הוא שהיה יושב וכותב
ארך אפים, matzao leHakadosh Baruch Hu shehayah yoshev vechotev erech apayim, God
was writing ארך אפים. erech apayim. אמר לפניו ריבונו של עולם, amar
lefanav Ribono shel olam, משה Moshe said to God, master of the
universe, ארך אפים לצדיקים, erech apayim latzadikim, it should only be for
the righteous. אמר לו אף לרשעים, amar lo af laresha'im, no, or
maybe it was just an ארך אפים לצדיקים? erech apayim latzadikim? And
he said no, אף לרשעים, af laresha'im, even the wicked people get
ארך אפים. erech apayim. אמר לו, amar lo, משה Moshe said to
him, רשעים יאבדו, resha'im yovedu, let the wicked, let them be destroyed,
who cares about the wicked? אמר ליה השתא חזית מאי דמבעי לך,
amar lei hashta chazit mai demiba'ei lach, now you'll see, mark your
words, משה, Moshe, you will need this מידה mida in the future.
כשחטאו ישראל, keshechate'u Yisrael, when the Jewish people sinned, אמר לו לא
כך אמרת לי ארך אפים לצדיקים, amar lo lo kach amarta li
erech apayim latzadikim, and and and so then when משה Moshe prayed
to God to forgive בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael for חטא העגל, cheit
ha'egel, God said to משה, Moshe, listen משה, Moshe, you recommended that
I only use my ארך אפים erech apayim for the צדיקים. tzadikim.
ק"יא עמוד ב. Kuf yud aleph amud bet. אמר לפניו, amar lefanav,
משה Moshe said to God, ריבונו של עולם ולא כך אמרת לי
אף לרשעים, Ribono shel olam velo kach amarta li af laresha'im, but
then you said to me, God, even for the wicked, and it's
with that מידה mida that I'm praying that you forgive the people.
היינו דכתיב Heinu dechtiv ועתה יגדל נא כוח ה' כאשר דיברת לאמור,
ve'ata yigdal na koach Hashem ka'asher dibarta lemor, God's power shall now
be great like you, God, have spoke, the way you said that
ארך אפים erech apayim was even for the רשעים. resha'im. Okay, רבי
חגא Rabbi Chaga הוה סליק ואזיל בדרגא דבי רבה hava salik ve'azil
bedarga debei Rabbah bar שילא, Shila, רבי חגא Rabbi Chaga was going
up on the step in the house of רבה Rabbah bar שילא,
Shila, שמעיה לההוא ינוקא דאמר, shameih lehahu yanuka de'amar, he heard a
child who was saying, עדותיך נאמנו מאוד לביתך נאוה קודש ה' לאורך
ימים, edotecha ne'emnu me'od leveitecha na'ava kodesh Hashem le'orech yamim, your testimonies
are are greatly faithful, you know, for your holy house, God, for
all future times. וסמיך ליה, vesamich lei, and was next to it
actually a few earlier פרקים, parakim, תפילה למשה, tefila leMoshe, a prayer
to משה. Moshe. אמר, amar, so he said, so רבי חגא Rabbi
Chaga said, שמע מינה, shma mina, so he took the reading of
this פסוק pasuk as, you know, paid attention to it as meaningful.
Maybe they were in the earlier similar discussion that we had just
a minute ago. ארך אפים ראה, erech apayim ra'ah, he saw. So
you see that because he says עדותיך נאמנו מאד, edotecha ne'emnu me'od,
they're very trustworthy, you know, and that that will be לאורך ימים,
le-orech yamim, maybe the אורך ימים orech yamim is ארך אפים, erech
apayim, so somehow that shows that משה Moshe was deeply grateful for
God's ארך אפים. erech apayim. Okay. אמר רבי אלעזר בר חנינא, Amar
Rabbi Elazar bar Chanina, עתיד הקדוש ברוך הוא להיות עטרה בראש כל
צדיק וצדיק. Atid HaKadosh Baruch Hu lihyot atarah be-rosh kol tzaddik ve-tzaddik.
God in the end will be a crown for the—so we are
now wrapping up because the next משנה mishnah gets us back to
הלכה, halakha, if you could believe it. So now we were sort
of taking care of some stuff we hadn't taken care of before.
We did with בני רשעי—you benei rishyei know, בני רשעי אומות העולם,
benei rishyei umot ha-olam, interestingly skipped the whole debate of צדיקי אומות
העולם. tzaddikei umot ha-olam. Then we did about like what's going to
happen, how much percent will be left in the time of גוג
ומגוג, Gog u-Magog, what percent of the people, and somehow now we
have switched also to a whole thing with, you know, with משה
Moshe and God and the מידות. midot. Okay. And now we are
saying like this: עתיד הקדוש ברוך הוא להיות עטרה בראש כל צדיק
וצדיק. Atid HaKadosh Baruch Hu lihyot atarah be-rosh kol tzaddik ve-tzaddik. In
the future times, God will be a crown—because we haven't really talked
so much about what that עולם הבא Olam HaBa will like look
like, you know, so God will be a crown on the head
of every righteous one, שנאמר ביום ההוא יהיה ה' צבאות לעטרת צבי
ולצפירת תפארה. shene'emar bayom hahu yihye Hashem tzevaot le-ateret tzevi u-le-tzfirat tiferah.
So exactly that: a crown of deer—of delight—and, you know, a crowning
glory לשאר עמו, li-she'ar amo, to the remnant of his people. So
that's the—again—the remnant. So מאי לעטרת צבי ולצפירת תפארה Mai le-ateret tzevi
u-le-tzfirat tiferah? לעושי רצונו ומצפים לישועתו. Le-osei retzono u-metzapim li-yeshuato. So those
that do God's will—maybe the ע' ayin for עושה oseh or עטרת
צבי, ateret tzevi, צבי tzevi is like צביון tzivyon is desire. So
לעושי רצונו ומצפים, le-osei retzono u-metzapim, צפירה tzfirah and those that look
forward לישועתו li-yeshuato for God's ultimate salvation, that have—like—wait for the משיח.
Mashiach. יכול לכל, Yachol lakol, maybe everybody? Now we just said it's
not everybody, we just said only those that do God's will. הגמרא
Ha-Gemara says, "Well, maybe it means even those that are arrogant?" Okay.
Anyway, יכול לכל, yachol lakol, maybe everybody, תלמוד לומר לשאר עמו, talmud
lomar li-she'ar amo, the remnant of his people. למי שמשים עצמו כשירים.
Le-mi she-mesim atzmo ke-shirayim. If you make yourself humble like שיריים, shirayim,
then you will be merit—you know, ultimately ימות המשיח. yemot ha-Mashiach. ולרוח
משפט ליושב על המשפט ולגבורה משיבי מלחמה שערה U-leruach mishpat le-yoshev al
ha-mishpat u-ligvurah meshivei milchamah sha'arah and for the spirit of justice to
the one who sits on justice and of valor who brings the
war back to the gate. ולרוח משפט, U-leruach mishpat, זה הרודה את
יצרו. zeh ha-rodeh et yitzro. So these are again reading it as
a continuation of the previous פסוק, pasuk, those that are going to
get God's crowning glory in the—in the future times. So זה הרודה
את יצרו, zeh ha-rodeh et yitzro, the one who sort of subjugates
his יצר, yetzer, you know, has a desire to do bad things
and forces himself to do good and to subjugate. ליושב על המשפט,
Le-yoshev al ha-mishpat, זה הדן דין אמת לאמיתו, zeh ha-dan din emet
le-amito, somebody who really is—brings justice into the land, true, old—true, deep
justice. ולגבורה, U-ligvurah, and for the valorous one, איזהו גיבור הכובש את
יצרו, eizehu gibor ha-kovesh et yitzro, זה המתגבר על יצרו, zeh ha-mitgaber
al yitzro, the one who is valorous over his יצר. yetzer. Not
exactly clear what the difference between רודה rodeh and מתגבר. mitgaber. רודה
rodeh maybe sounds like you're still in a struggle, מתגבר mitgaber you
have been victorious, means you have completely subjugated it. רש"י Rashi also
says like מתגבר mitgaber could mean you sort of sublimate it and
turn that into something good, not just stopping from doing something bad.
משיבי מלחמה, Meshivei milchamah, those who return the war, זה שנושא ונותן
במלחמתה של תורה, zeh she-noseh ve-noten be-milchamtah shel Torah, somebody who does
the back and the forth, you know, the—the type—the battle of Torah,
those are the ones that will get עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. שערה,
Sha'arah, the gate, אלו שמשכימים ומעריבים בבתי כנסיות ובבתי מדרשות, elu she-mashkimim
u-ma'arivim be-vatei khnesiyot u-vatei midrashot, those that go—get up early and leave
late in the בית מדרש beit midrash and the בית כנסת. beit
knesset. אמרה מדת הדין לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amra midat ha-din lifnei
ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono shel Olam, מה נשתנו אלו
מאלו mah nishtanu elu me-elu? God, how is these different than these?
Okay? Which is meaning that, you know, how did these merit to
get—the way רש"י Rashi says, obviously they're different, they're—they're learning Torah, they're
humble, they're doing God's מצוות, mitzvot, but what made them different? What
made them different from all those who did not follow this path?
אמר ליה, Amar leh, God said: וגם אלה ביין שגו ובשכר תעו
ופקו פליליה. ve-gam eleh be-yayin shagu u-va-shechar ta'u u-paku peliliyah. So even
those who like now the sinners, you know, they erred with wine,
okay, and with—and with hard—hard drink. So yeah, everybody else was just
lazy and drunk, and these people applied themselves to תורה ומצוות. Torah
u-mitzvot. ואין פוקה אלא גיהנם, Ve-ein pukah ela Gehenom, and what is
ופקו פליליה paku peliliyah? פוקה Pukah means of the—gets גיהנם, Gehenom, שנאמר
לא תהיה לך זאת לפוקה. shene'emar lo tihyeh lecha zot le-pukah. ואין
פלילה אלא דיינים, Ve-ein pelilah ela dayanim, and פלילה pelilah means judges,
they'll be judged in גיהנם, Gehenom, שנאמר ונתן בפלילים. shene'emar ve-natan bi-flilim.
So the ultimate message at the end is if you want to
get עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, do מצוות mitzvot and—and really devote yourself
to the study of תורה. Torah. Okay, let's keep on going. Now
we finally gets to a משנה, mishnah, which is the reason this
חלק chelek is not the last פרק perek in סנהדרין Sanhedrin is
because the last משנה mishnah in—in this is about אנשי עיר הנדחת,
anshei ir ha-nidachat, whether אין להם חלק לעולם הבא, ein lahem chelek
le-olam ha-ba, they don't have a portion in the world to come.
So this really comes when we're talking about עיר הנדחת, ir ha-nidachat,
when you go back to the פרק, perek, you know, which was—which
was before, what do you call it... You know, הנשרפין hanisrafin was
dealing with those that get הרג, hereg, and it did not ever
get in the משניות mishnayot to discussing אנשי עיר הנדחת anshei ir
hanidachat who get הרג. hereg. So really what it should have happened
when נשרפין nisrafin did הרג hereg and did a lot of the
הרג hereg particularly רוצח rotzeach was a big one if you remember,
then חלק, chelek, which all of the things about who does and
doesn't get a portion to the עולם הבא olam haba is because
we're going to discuss whether אנשי עיר הנדחת anshei ir hanidachat have
a portion in the עולם הבא, olam haba, and then we're going
to discuss the הלכות halachos of אנשי עיר הנדחת anshei ir hanidachat
and they get הרג, hereg, and then we have the real final
פרק perek which is אלו הן הנחנקים. eileh hen hanichnakim. Okay, so
that's how it all structures together. Anyways, let's take a look. This
משנה. mishnah. אנשי עיר הנדחת אין להם חלק לעולם הבא, Anshei ir
hanidachat ein lahem chelek l'olam haba, the people of a city that
all worships עבודה זרה avoda zara doesn't have a portion of the
world to come, שנאמר יצאו אנשים בני בליעל מקרבך, shene'emar yatze'u anashim
bnei beliya'al mikirbecha, people, you know, without a rebellious or whatever people
went out from your midst, וידיחו את יושבי עירם, vayadichu et yoshvei
iram, and they pushed off the dwellers of the city, meaning they
seduced them to idolatry. It is not exactly clear how that means
they don't have a portion, but we'll see it together in the
גמרא. Gemara. יצאו, yatze'u, they left entirely being part of בני ישראל,
Bnei Yisrael, you know, they left their portion. Okay. Now we're going
to get to their הלכות. halachos. ואינם נהרגים עד שיהיו מדיחיה מאותה
העיר. V'einam neheragim ad sheyiyu madicheha me'otah ha'ir. It's only considered an
עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat as opposed to what people get הרג, hereg,
that's אינם נהרגים, einam neheragim, you know, they get הרג, hereg, only
if it's the majority of the city and all these criteria that
we're about to list, and if not then it's just a lot
of separate individuals who sinned and each one gets סקילה sekilah for
עבודה זרה avoda zara but you don't destroy, you don't burn the
city, you don't destroy their money and so on. So that's the
basic difference. If it's individuals, it's סקילה sekilah but that's it, nothing
about destroying property and all burning the city, and if it's the
majority of the city plus all the criteria that we're going to
see, then they get הרג hereg and then you destroy the whole
city, you burn the whole city. Okay. ואינם נהרגים עד שיהיו מדיחיה
מתוך העיר. V'einam neheragim ad sheyiyu madicheha mitoch ha'ir. So in order
to make it an עיר הנדחת, ir hanidachat, you they the those
the מדיחים, madichim, the seducers, have to be from the from the
city itself, citizens of the city, מדיחיה מאותה העיר, madicheha me'otah ha'ir,
ומאותו שבט, um'oto shevet, and from the same tribe as the city.
The גמרא Gemara will discuss how could you have them as citizens
of the city and not the same tribe. ועד שיודח רובה, V'ad
sheyudach rubah, the majority of the city has to worship עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. ועד שידיחו אנשים, V'ad sheyadichu anashim, and the and also
the seducers, the people that are, you know, leading them astray have
to be men, not women or not children. הדיחוה נשים וקטנים, Hidichuha
nashim uktanim, if it was women or children that were the enticers,
או שהודח מיעוטה, o shehudach mi'utah, or only a minority of the
city worshipped עבודה זרה, avoda zara, או שהיו מדיחיה חוצה לה, o
shehayu madicheha chutzah lah, or the enticers came from outside the city,
in all these cases, הרי אלו כיחידים, harei elu kiyachidim, it might
be it might be a lot, lot of individuals but they're all
treated as individuals. It doesn't have the status of an עיר הנדחת.
ir hanidachat. וצריכים שני עדים והתראה לכל אחד ואחד, Utzrichim shnei eidim
vehatra'ah l'chol echad v'echad, every individual needs two witnesses and warning, and
warning. Okay. Okay. Now, וזה חומר ביחידים ממרובים, v'zeh chomer biyachidim mimerubim,
and that would, you know, that would be true regardless of whether
it's an עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat or it's individuals, you first have
to start obligating each individual and then if it tallies up to
רוב rov and the other criteria are met, then you'll have an
עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachat. Okay. זה חומר ביחידים ממרובים שהיחידים בסקילה, Zeh
chomer biyachidim mimerubim shehayachidim biskilah, this is the way in this way
if it's just at the status of individuals it's more severe than
עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat because individuals they get סקילה, sekilah, לפיכך ממונם
פליט, lefichach mamonam palit, but the counter-balance to that is even though
the מיתה misah was a more severe one, their money doesn't get
destroyed, right? It is an interesting question, why is the מיתה misah
more severe by the case of the individual? Maybe you have less
culpability as an individual, I mean more culpability as an individual because
it's not like everybody's doing and you were taken away by the
influence of the masses. So you're very, very culpable but it does
not have this broader sense of destroying all the property. Okay. והמרובים
בסייף, Vehamerubim besayif, but if it becomes the majority, the whole city,
then they get the sword, לפיכך ממונם אבד, lefichach mamonam avad, but
they also they get a lighter מיתה misah but they get the
more strict consequence of destroying all the property. Okay. הכה תכה יושבי
העיר ההיא לפי חרב, Hakeh takeh yoshvei ha'ir hahi lefi charev, smite
the members of that city by the sword. החמרת והגמלת, Hachameret vehagamalet,
now let's say you have a donkey driver or camel driver העובר
ממקום למקום, ha'over mimakom limakom, that's passing through the city. Do you
count them as part of the city in order to determine whether
like if they didn't worship עבודה זרה avoda zara will that make
it that it's יחידים, yachidim, if they did worship עבודה זרה avoda
zara and they tipped the scales in the other direction will that
make it, you know, like they're the מרובים? merubim? You have to
know who counts as the population of the city to decide whether
you have a majority or not. So what's the story with these?
Okay, הרי אלו מצילים אותה, harei elu matzilim otah, so if they
they would be considered part of the city. And if they did
not worship עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* and that turned it into a
minority, you know, only a minority worshipped עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* because
you’re counting these as well, then the whole city does not get
destroyed. רש"י *Rashi* points out the same would be in the reverse,
if because they worshipped עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* and they’re counted as
members of the city they made it a majority, the city would
get destroyed, okay? But we’d rather talk about a nicer outcome. All
right. And the גמרא *Gemara* will discuss how long they have to
be in the city in order to be considered members of the
city. Okay. Now, okay, so that’s that. החרם אותה *hacherem osah*, we
don't have the שנאמר *shenemar*. החרם אותה ואת כל אשר בה ואת
בהמתה לפי חרב *hacherem osah ve-es kol asher bah ve-es behemtah lefi
charev*, destroy it and all that is in it and you know,
all the animals by the sword. מכאן אמרו *mikan amru*, נכסי צדיקים
שבתוכה אבודים *nichsei tzadikim she-be-tochah avudim*, that if it’s, if it’s את
כל שללה *es kol shelalah*, you know, כל אשר בה *kol asher
bah*, everything in it, even the property of the צדיקים *tzadikim*, of
the people that didn't worship עבודה זרה *avodah zarah*, the property would
be destroyed because it says את כל אשר בה *es kol asher
bah*. צדיקים שבתוכה אבודים *tzadikim she-be-tochah avudim*. שבחוץ פלטים *she-be-chutz pletim*, but
if it’s, if it’s the righteous people in the city and it’s
their property outside of the city, that you do not destroy. ושל
רשעים *ve-shel reshaim*, but the property of the רשעים *reshaim*, the wicked,
בין שבתוכה בין שבחוץ הרי אלו אובדים *bein she-be-tochah bein she-be-chutz harei
elu ovdim*, you would destroy the property of the wicked people the
city who did worship עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* even if their property
was outside the city. Not clear where we get that from from
the פסוק *pasuk*, we’ll see about that in the גמרא *Gemara*. Okay.
Take all the שנאמר *shenemar*s here. ואת כל שללה *ve-es kol shelalah*,
what we’re doing is quoting a פסוק *pasuk* explaining the הלכה *halacha*,
quoting a פסוק *pasuk* explaining the הלכה *halacha*. The פסוק *pasuk* precedes
the discussion, not follows it. Okay. ואת כל שללה תקבוץ אל תוך
רחובה *ve-es kol shelalah tikbotz el toch rechovah*, gather all of its
booty into the, you know, into the street. אם אין לה רחוב
עושים לה רחוב *im ein lah rechov osim lah rechov*. If it
doesn't have a street, make it a street. You can even make
a new street. You know, the alternative would have been to say
if it doesn't have a street, it's a technicality and it gets
off. היתה רחובה חוצה לה כונסין אותה לתוכה *haysah rechovah chutzah lah
konesin osah le-tochah*. If their main street was outside of it, you
divert the main street into the city so it has a street.
Not exactly clear how that’s different than the previous point of just
make it a street. Okay. ושרפת באש את העיר ואת כל שללה
כליל לה' אלוהיך *ve-saraftah ba-esh es ha-ir ve-es kol shelalah kalil la-Hashem
Elohecha*. You shall burn it in the fire, you know, in the
fire the city and all of its booty completely to ה' *Hashem*.
שלה ולא של שמיים *shelah ve-lo shel shamayim*, only its booty but
not something that ultimately is the property of heaven. מכאן אמרו *mikan
amru*, הקדשות שבה יפדו *hekdeshos she-bah yipadu*. If you have something that
is sanctified, you redeem it and you do not destroy it. ותרומות
ירקבו *u-trumos yirkavu*. And if you have תרומה *trumah*, you let it
rot. Now what’s very strange about this is, it is that it
is not telling you that, you know, okay, it's telling you you
don't burn it, but it’s also not telling you you can walk
away and use it. The things that are הקדש *hekdesh* get this
weird, weird middle state that you’re not going to directly destroy them,
but you also have to let them become wasted and you can’t
use them. All right. We’ll talk about more of that tomorrow. Okay.
הקדשות שבה יפדו *hekdeshos she-bah yipadu*, ותרומות ירקבו *u-trumos yirkavu*, you let
the תרומה *trumah* rot. מעשר שני וכתבי הקודש יגנזו *ma'aser sheni ve-kisvei
ha-kodesh yignazu*, and מעשר שני *ma'aser sheni* and, you know, and holy
scripture you have to bury. So you can’t use it, you just
don't directly burn it. So it’s this weird middle state. כליל לה'
אלוהיך *kalil la-Hashem Elohecha*, fully to ה' *Hashem* your God. אמר רבי
שמעון *amar Rabbi Shimon*, אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא *amar Ha-kadosh Baruch Hu*,
אם אתם עושים דין בעיר הנידחת מעלה אני עליכם כאילו אתם מעלים
עולה כליל לפניי *im atem osim din be-ir ha-nidachas ma'aleh ani aleichem
k'ilu atem ma'alim olah kalil lefanai*. So the word כליל *kalil* evokes
the idea of an עולה *olah* completely burned up. So He says
if you will do the judgment of the עיר הנידחת *ir ha-nidachas*,
you know, it’s very hard to destroy an entire city, kill out,
I mean, you would have killed the individuals who worshipped עבודה זרה
*avodah zarah* anyway, but it’s such a horrific thing. If you’re able
to do that, I’ll treat the whole thing as a burnt offering.
והיתה תל עולם *ve-haysah tel olam*, it will be an eternal תל
*tel*, like a mound. לא תעשה גנות ופרדסים דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי
*lo te-aseh ganos u-fardesim divrei Rabbi Yose Ha-Gelili*. רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi
Yose Ha-Gelili* says you can’t even use it for like a garden.
Not only can you not rebuild it as a city, you can’t
even use it for a garden. ולא תבנה עוד *ve-lo tibaneh od*
is what it says there. רבי עקיבא אומר *Rabbi Akiva omer*, לא
תבנה עוד *lo tibaneh od*, כמות שהיתה אינה נבנית אבל נעשית היא
גנות ופרדסים *kemos she-haysah einah nivnes aval na'ases hi ganos u-fardesim*. You
can’t rebuild it like a city, כמות שהיתה *kemos she-haysah*, אינה נבנית
*einah nivnes*, but it can be used to be made as gardens.
Last פסוק *pasuk*, ולא ידבק בידך מאומה מן החרם *ve-lo yidbak be-yadcha
me-umah min ha-cherem*. Nothing of the sort of stuff under the ban
shall cleave to your hand. שכל זמן שהרשעים בעולם חרון אף בעולם
*she-kol zman she-ha-reshaim ba-olam charon af ba-olam*. So it’s as long as
the רשעים *reshaim* are in the world, God’s anger is in the
world. אבדו רשעים מן העולם נסתלק חרון אף מן העולם *avdu reshaim
min ha-olam nistalek charon af min ha-olam*. Okay, because the end of
the פסוק *pasuk* is למען ישוב ה' מחרון אפו *lema'an yashuv Hashem
me-charon apo*. Okay, so once the רשעים *reshaim* are wicked, are destroyed,
then God’s anger will be, will be, you know, removed from the
world. Okay, we’ll end.